[Music]
foreign
ERS of American adults drink coffee
about half of which on a daily basis and
that comes out to a million tons of
coffee every year might there be grounds
for concern population Studies have
found that coffee drinkers tend to have
lower risk of Parkinson's less prostate
cancers especially the women less liver
cancer less diabetes liver cirrhosis
depression among women and a reduction
in mortality overall such that coffee
drinkers tend to live longer than
non-coffee drinkers with mortality
bottoming out at about four cups a day
but these are all just associations you
don't know if it's cause and effect
until you put it to the test and for
example coffee really does seem to
protect the liver and take people with
chronic hepatitis and have them drink
coffee or not for a month then switch
them back and the coffee really did seem
to help
similarly a randomized Parkinson's
patients to get two cups of coffee worth
of caffeine and get a significant
Improvement in movement symptoms within
three weeks Runners randomized to drink
coffee shaved about six seconds off
their mile weight lifters randomized
coffee can squat more weight about 600
pounds more worth of reps and not just
athletic performance a cup of coffee's
worth of caffeine can significantly
improve
i-e-l-t which stands for intravaginal
ejaculation latency time from two
minutes all the way up to five
unfortunately those effectively
randomized at births to genetically just
have higher predilection to drink coffee
do not appear to be protected from
diabetes or depression or Alzheimer's or
obesity or metabolic syndrome so it
seems the protective associations may
just be due to confounding factors like
maybe those who drink coffee and just
happen to exercise more or something and
the same with prostate cancer no
apparent cause and effect relationship
and even the mortality benefit seemed to
disappear
even if a study did show coffee drinking
could extend lifespan by reducing
inflammation or improving lung function
or insulin sensitivity that would mean
on average there is
inter-individual variability after
consumption of major plant food
compounds meaning people May respond
differently
for example how crazy is this in some
rare individuals heavy use of caffeine
apparently provokes sleepiness
that that's an extreme example most of
the time it's just that you know some
individuals may benefit more than others
from the health effects of different
foods for example because of differences
in gut bacteria only a minority of
westerners May derive extra benefit from
soy as I've described before the most
common difference in caffeine effects is
that well most people metabolize
caffeine rapidly certain Gene variants
in liver detox enzymes make some people
slow metabolizers might that make a
difference well habitual coffee
consumption of at least three cups a day
has been associated with uncontrolled
blood pressure among older individuals
diagnosed with hypertension suggesting
that moderating coffee intake may be a
good idea for some people but even if it
was cause and effect I mean that would
be on average what would happen if you
split people up by how fast they
metabolize caffeine compared to Coffee
abstainers those who have impaired
caffeine metabolism genes have an
elevated risk of becoming hypertensive
at you know one to three cups a day and
especially at four or more
okay but check this out for the rapid
metabolizers Not only was there no
excess risk at one of three cups heavy
coffee drinkers were protected meaning
apparently the more coffee they drank
the lower their risk
how do we explain that
well coffee is a complex blend of a vast
number of different compounds there are
protective polyphenol antioxidants that
are beneficial coffee beans are after
all beans well actually seeds but seeds
are really healthy too on the other hand
there's the caffeine which can Spike
adrenaline levels in the blood but only
if you're a slow metabolizer rapid
metabolism can clear caffeine so fast
that there's no increase in Adrenaline
even at you know four more cups a day
and so then you just have the beneficial
polyphenols that actually lower your
blood pressure hence the benefit overall
thus there seems to be a Jekyll and Hyde
aspect of coffee whose overall action on
the cardiovascular system appears to be
regulated by that Gene for the enzyme
that metabolizes caffeine
the important question though is does it
give women larger breasts
what young women who drink a lot of
coffee in a rapid caffeine metabolizes
have about a half a baseball sized
larger breast volume which may be a bad
thing as breast volume is associated
with breast cancer risk but now the the
important question is what about heart
attack risk
in slow metabolizers daily coffee
consumption appeared to double the odds
of a heart attack or even quadruple the
odds at four cups a day whereas in the
rapid caffeine metabolizers daily coffee
consumption was protective cutting the
odds of a heart attack by more than half
or at least until you get up to four
more cups a day the protective effects
observed among rapid metabolizers
suggest that the efficient elimination
of caffeine might have unmasked the
protective effects of other
phytochemicals in coffee
now we think it may be the adrenaline
again since if you're a slow metabolizer
of adrenaline
High Coffee consumption may put you at
risk as well
so
is coffee Friend or Foe these studies
suggest the possibility that slow
caffeine metabolizes who consume
caffeinated coffee may have an increased
risk of cardiovascular disease whereas
fast caffeine metabolizes may be
protected from this risk by the
antioxidants and other beneficial
compounds present
foreign